<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A back-blow to Major Huntington, for his treacherous accusation of Lieutenant Generall Cromwell, and Commissary Gen. Ireton. Published for generall satisfaction of all, who have unadvisedly received the malicious accusation against those active gentlemen.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E461_34</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205205</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864636</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864636</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116868</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76638)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116868)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 73:E461[34])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A back-blow to Major Huntington, for his treacherous accusation of Lieutenant Generall Cromwell, and Commissary Gen. Ireton. Published for generall satisfaction of all, who have unadvisedly received the malicious accusation against those active gentlemen.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Sept ye 1st 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ireton, Henry, 1611-1651 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Cromwell, Oliver, 1599-1658 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>England and Wales. --  Army --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116868:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A BACK-BLOW TO Major Huntington, FOR His Treacherous accuſation OF Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and Commiſſary Gen. IRETON.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>Publiſhed for generall ſatisfaction of all, who have unadviſedly received the malicieus accuſation againſt thoſe active Gentlemen.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THat no man might be miſtaken in judging what principles beare rule in this Major; in the firſt lines of his diſcourſe, he fully demonſtrats himſelfe <hi>to be for the King,</hi> being no whit aſhamed to avouch, (that which now all good men bluſh at, to remember) <hi>that he tooke up Armes, in defence of the authoritie &amp; power of King</hi>— and Parliament: which he receits, as rejoycing this miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116868:2"/>doubtfull and enſnaring conjunction ſhould be minded, rather then the juſt disjoyning of them in the now Lord Gen. Commiſſion; &amp; is a marke that fails not to tell you, that he is abſolutely the Kings, as all others are, who uſe it in theſe knowing times; moſt of them being as much in their hearts for the King, as him ſelfe was in words for the Parliament, which he never failed in all his writings to proclaime, <hi>but in deeds, this Major and his Majeſty will prove both alike to Parliaments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And however he pretends him ſelfe tyed both in duty and conſcience, (under the notion of rendering his true reaſons of quitting his employment in the Army) to accuſe Lieutenant Generall <hi>Cromwell,</hi> and Commiſſary Generall <hi>Jreton,</hi> yet the whole ſcope of his <hi>Narrative</hi> will manifeſt, that moſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiouſly he doth it, in purſuance of the Kings ſervice, as being hopefull thereby to worke diviſions in the Army, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath failed to make it wholy uſefull to him (which he ever aymed at) yet poſſibly now by new diſtempers to make it uſeles to it ſelfe, or if he failed thereof, yet to work new jealouſies and quarells betwixt the Parliament &amp; the Army, either of wihich could not but be more advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to the King, then any thing he could doe for him in holding his employment, and which is in deed the true cauſe wherefore he left it.</p>
            <p>And for which the King is highly beholding to him; for to do him this ſpeciall peece of ſervice, he hath layed himſelf open to all the world, to be the moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious diſſembler that this age hath known, and therefore though he faile of his purpoſe, and that the ſervice intended, be likely to prove a dis-ſervice, yet it were a great pitty, that to officious a Traytor, ſhould not receive a Traytors reward from one hand or other; in the mean time, this is his portion, he will be to himſelf like <hi>Cain,</hi> poſſeſſing a Conſcience only to torment him, all that have any thing of Chriſtianity or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity in them will abhorre him, nor is he likely to have a ſpeeedy end of his vexation, but by a Judas courſe: for he hath endeavored to bring to deſtruction his moſt intimate familiar friends, not for doing the things he ſayes they did,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116868:2"/>but becauſe all thoſe things were ſteered to an honeſter end then he intended.</p>
            <p>And hence it is, he now complaines to the Parliament, that he hath left the Army, becauſe <hi>the principles, deſignes and actions of thoſe Officers, which have a great influence upon the Army, are (as he conceives) very repugnant to the honour and ſafety of the Parliament and King — dum, from whom they derive their authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus ſpoken, he thinks he is ſafe enough, from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuſpected to be for the King, and therefore as a moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſcienced and wel-affected Major, <hi>he boldly proceedes and charges theſe Gentlemen, the Lieutenant Gen, and Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary General; with breach of Parliamentary truſt committed to them at</hi> Walden, <hi>that inſtead of reducing the Army to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Parliament, they not only diſcountenanced thoſe that were obedient, but encouraged the diſobedient, declaring that there had been lately much cruelty and injuſtice in the Parliaments proceedings againſt the Army, that Commiſſary General</hi> Ireton <hi>there framed the papers and writings ſent thence to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That Lieutenant Generall</hi> Cromwell <hi>ſaid, they were in a double capacity, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Then, that at Triple Heath, they inſtructed the Souldiers to cry justice, juſtice, — then that they without allowance of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, or knowledge of the Generall, contrived and ſetcht the King from</hi> Holmby, <hi>that they animated the private Souldiers and Agitators therein, and in ſecuring the Gariſon of</hi> Oxford, <hi>and the Ammunition there, — ſhewes the Generalls diſtike of removing the King, and that the Lieutenant Gen, ſaid, that if it had not been done, the King would have been ſetcht away by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Parliament, or conveyed away by Col.</hi> Graves <hi>to</hi> London, <hi>&amp;c. That Cornet</hi> Joyce <hi>affirmed that the Lieutenant Generall ordered him at</hi> London <hi>to do that he did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ſubſtance of the firſt part of his accuſation of theſe Gentlemen,—in juſtification of whom there needes no more but this; its known the Parliament was ſo unhappy as to be ſteered by ſome politick men into a courſe, directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the intereſt and freedom of the Common-wealth, dayly vexing and moleſting conſcientious people for non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116868:3"/>conformity to Presbyterian Government, examining them <hi>ex officio, impriſoning them during pleaſure, and animated the City in their corrupt Remonſtrance;</hi> by which all men were excluded from office (military or other) that ſubmitted not to the Presbytery.</p>
            <p>And when redreſſe of theſe grievances was ſought for from Parliament, the influence of thoſe Polititians was ſo great, that the Petitions of all the honeſt parties grieved, were ſentenced to be burnt by the common Hangman: Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever accuſed any of theſe domineering men, was in danger to be cruſht; as Mr. <hi>Guerdon</hi> a Member of the Houſe was, for appearing againſt Col. <hi>Hollis,</hi> about his ſoliciting the King to come to <hi>London;</hi> ſome being impriſoned for appearing therein.</p>
            <p>Its known what libellous bookes, and ſcandalous ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons were publiſhed, licenced and preached continually a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Army, and that divers Souldiers were then hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſome otherwiſe puniſhed at Aſſizes and Seſſions for doing faithfull and needfull ſervice to the Parliament, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their Orders and Ordinances: and whilſt things were in this dangerous poſture, and the Major part of the Parliament wrought into this evill conſtitution, occaſion is taken to vote the disbanding of the Army, under pretence of ſervice for <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now its well known, that in all theſe evill times and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of the Houſe of Commons from their firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and practices, there was a conſiderable number of the Members that oppoſed thoſe time-ſerving men very boldly and couragiouſly, their debates were high and publikely known, both to the Army, and all over the Land, and the worſer party ſeldom carried any thing, but the Houſe was forced to divide, ſo that matters of the higheſt nature were carried ſomtimes by ſix, and other times by three voices only.</p>
            <p>In all which time, none were more openly oppoſite to whatſoever was illegall or deſtructive to freedom, then the Lieutenant Gen. and Commiſſary Gen. ſo as their judgments were fully known; and if they had not declared themſelves,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116868:3"/>yet if any had but put or imagined themſelves in their caſes, they might eaſily have judged, with what ſafety to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they could have conſented to the disbanding of the Army, when no ſooner it had been done, but their much ſought for lives, had lyen at the cruell mercy of their moſt wicked and malicious adverſaries, one of them having been more then threatned by a chiefe of the faction.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſſe, to entangle them throughly, and either ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate them to diſobey the Parliament, or deſtroy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and all that any wiſe adhered to them, who but the Lieut. Generall, and Commiſſary Generall, are appointed by Order of Parliament to disband the Army?</p>
            <p>In this caſe now, if they gave heed to the dictats of their own conſciences, rather then to that deſtructive Order of Parliament; have they not the Law of nature, the proceedings of this Parliament againſt the King, and the Scots firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into this Kingdom, to juſtifie the preſervation of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelvs, the whole Army and their friends; had they not been Traytors to all theſe, and to juſtice it ſelfe, if they had obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Commands ſo deſtructive?</p>
            <p>And it muſt in concluſion be a received truth by all, that if any authority, yea if Parliaments ſhall turn tyrants, even Parliaments themſelves muſt and ought to be reſiſted, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe what tye is there upon the ſupream authority?</p>
            <p>But this ſubject is ſo rationally and fully cleared in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies Declaration of the 14. of Iune 1647, that it is needles here to infiſt upon, nor was Major <hi>Huntington</hi> a proteſter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Declaration; then it ſeems, he was well pleaſed to ſee the Army and Parliament at ſo great a difference, as hoping in time by that meanes, to make ſome faire advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage for the King his Maſter.</p>
            <p>And what now doth all this large accuſation amount to? but that thoſe who ſo cunningly ſought to entangle theſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, that which way ſoever they took, they ſhould be ruined, was by their wiſdom circumvented, and the evill intended fell on their own heads, as (doubtles) this evill will fall upon this Majors head one time or other; and had he been but as wiſe as he is officious, their ill ſucceſſe in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116868:4"/>their unjuſt attempts, might have ſufficed for a fair war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to him.</p>
            <p>As for his ſingling out theſe two Gentlemen about remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the King, or any thing elſe in his accuſation, his malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous end may be eaſily perceived, theſe having prevailed moſt againſt the King when he was at ſtrongeſt, and through them it is no leſſe diſcernable, that he ſtrickes at the Generall himſelf, though in the narrative of this accuſation, he would ſeem to exclude him; every man knowing it, as unexcuſable to hold, as to remove without or againſt Order, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all from head to foote, even the whole Army alike engaged.</p>
            <p>And it had been an extream weakneſſe in them, to have ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded the King out of their own cuſtody, perceiving the earneſt deſirs of their numerous and malicious adverſaries, to make uſe of him to the Armies ruin; all this wind ſhakes not, &amp; the Major might have ſpared his unſavory breath in blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this coale a freſh; all that he hath ſaid hitherto, being far better known to be owned by the whole Army, then he can expreſſe, whereof he thought himſelf no ſmall one, putting himſelf forward, that ſo he might have opportunity to lead to his own, and the King his Maſters ends.</p>
            <p>In the next place, the Lieut. Generall is charged to make it his buſines <hi>to Court his Majeſty, both by Members of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> (whereof this officious Major was one) <hi>and ſeverall Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen formerly in the Kings ſervice, into a good opinion of the proceedings of the Army,</hi> which then were really good and juſtifiable; <hi>as alſo into a diſaffection to, and diſlike of the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of Parliament,</hi> (which then were really evill and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive though not to the Kings deſigns, which cauſed him ſo often to alledge as this Major ſayes) that the power by which they fought, was the power of Parliament, it ſeems that power was then uſed more for the Kings ends then eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one knew, though well known to the King, and now ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonablie remembered by this his Major, though to little purpoſe.</p>
            <p>For what followeth? why that the Lieut. Generall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed, <hi>that the Army would be for the King,</hi> in what, In do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116868:4"/>injury to any? No, <hi>but in the ſettlement of his whole buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> What was that? Read but their Declaration of the 14. of <hi>Iune</hi> 1647. and it will appear <hi>to be a work ſo heedfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, as to the freedom and ſecurity of the people,</hi> that the Lieut. Generall and his ſonne <hi>Ireton</hi> need never to be aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for that; And for what did he ſo work the King (Major) and ſo promiſe him; Upon what condition? — <hi>but that the King and his party would ſit ſtill and not declare againſt the Aymy, but give them leave only to manage the preſent buſines in hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what is it that troubles this <hi>Major</hi> in all this? Is it becauſe theſe gentlemen were ſo kinde to the King? No, but that they have not been ſoe careleſſe of themſelves, as to give him opportunity to deſtroy them; for they ſoone found that the King could better diſgeſt any principles, then thoſe of Independencie, and that they had good reaſon to awaite up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his wings, and to keep good guards upon him, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiveing well where he had a minde to be; &amp; though the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor be pleaſed to make this a peece of a charge againſt them yet had it been his owne caſe, (and he honeſtly minded) he would have done no leſſe, nor would he have been diverted from ſo neceſſary a care, with the bigg words or high looks of any.</p>
            <p>But then he ſayes the Parliament complyed with the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, after which the King inclined to hearken unto the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies deſires, and not before; ſo it appeares as then the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament was his pilot, though as to the people, it had ſteered a very dangerous courſe, but neither King nor Parliament can erre in this Majors divinitie, his part it ſeemes, is to charge only the Lieutenant Gen. and Commiſſary Gen. and he is reſolved to be true (as long as he can or gets by it) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, or till the King put him upon ſome other part or deſigne.</p>
            <p>Then he chargeth them, that <hi>at Caverſham, the King was continually ſolicited by Meſſengers from Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Gen. Cromwell, and Commiſſary Gen. Ireton, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring any thing his Majeſtie ſhould deſire, as Revennes,</hi> how much, he ſayes not, and ſuch might be meant, as might not
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116868:5"/>be prejudiciall to any? <hi>next Chaplaines;</hi> and if the ſtate were wiſe, what hurt could they do? <hi>Then wife Children, Servants of his own, viſitation of friends, acceſſe of letters,</hi> all theſe were not evills eſſentially, &amp; were profered only upon condition of the quietneſſe of himſelf and his party, which doubtleſſe they reſolved to ſee performed.</p>
            <p>But then (which troubles the Major moſt of all) the King he ſayes was further promiſed by Commiſſary Gen. <hi>Ireton, that his negative voice ſhould not be medled withall;</hi> and believe it, this is matter for any honeſt true hearted <hi>Engliſhman</hi> to be troubled at<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea, he goes on ſaying, <hi>the Commiſſary Generall ſhould tell his Majeſty, that he had convinced thoſe that reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt it, in the generall Councell of the Army; and all this they would do, that his Majeſty might the better ſee into all our actions, and know our principles, which lead us to give him all thoſe things out of conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>For that we were not a people hateing his Majeſties perſon or monarchicall government, but that we liked it as the beſt, (and that by this King) ſaying alſo, that they did hold it a very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable thing for the Parliament to abridge him of them: of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten promiſing, that if the King would ſit ſtill, and not act againſt them,</hi> they would in the firſt place, reſtore him to all theſe, <hi>and upon the ſettlement of our own juſt rights and liberties, make him the moſt glorious Prince in Chriſtendom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here indeed, was too much comprized <hi>by the negative voice</hi> at the leaſt, and ſome contradiction too; for how could juſt rights and liberties conſiſt with a negative voice, or how could he be made the moſt glorious Prince, that ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed ſo black a ſpot of tyranny, as is a negative voice, and which therefore would enforce a beliefe, that the Major was miſtaken, and reported this ſtory rather as he would have is then truly? but admit all be true, (which will never be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved by thoſe, who from much intimacy have had diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of a quite contrary nature from thoſe Gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) yet thus much may be ſaid in their behalf, that at this time the King made uſe of the preſent diſtempers in <hi>London,</hi> and ſtood very high upon his points, and could not otherwiſe be drawn to decline the party oppoſing the army, but upon ſuch promiſes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116868:5"/>and workings, as their too much feare of his party wrought from them, rather then any deſire to be officious unto him, in things ſo oppoſite to liberty and their own judgments; doubtleſſe they were full of care, and in great perplexity, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving begun ſo high an enterprize, that the like had not been in mans memory.</p>
            <p>And its evident, the condition of his ſitting ſtil was all in all in theſe promiſes, without wich the King would not be ſatisfied; ſo if an error, t'was for peace ſake, not for their own ends, but for publick quietnes—But why is the Major now troubled about theſe things, except becauſe they are not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed? he (it ſeemes) hath done nothing elſe but diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled all this time, for the baſeſt of ends ambition and coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, even to betray his owne native liberties, and the juſt freedomes of the whole Nation.</p>
            <p>And what if at the ſame time, all on the Kings parte, was done onely to amuſe them, and in time to be diſcovered to their diſparagment, how if at that inſtant or before, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſon were conveyed to Colonell <hi>Maſſie,</hi> how if the King had before laid thoſe <hi>Scots</hi> Egges that now are hatch't, and the King was reſolved to caſt him ſelfe any way<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rather then on the Independent intereſt, as being incompatible with his, and that there was never any realitie on his part towards them, what then Major? As for any offence this might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Parliament, in the Parliaments ſenſe, all they did was offence: ſo that all this is only thus much, the King was (not ſo ſimple as he hath been deemed, but rather) too ſuttle for them in this ſtate work, and not much neither, all things reehoned.</p>
            <p>And touching all the buſineſſes which he receiteth about the propoſalls, they are but things of the ſame nature, for all that endeavoured by theſe Gentlemen thereby, was to keepe the King and his party quiet, and all that he intended, was firſt or laſt to divide, diſparage, and weaken them by diſputes and debates, about pleaſing him in thoſe propoſalls, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly it ſoon took effect, though not ſo much as was expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but it had been greater and more dangerous, if the Londo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners had not been ſoe for ward in their violent courſes againſt the Parliament, thereby putting the army upon ſpeedy mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116868:6"/>unexpected returning, &amp; urgent employment to pacify that tumult, which united them beyond imagination: yet what by thoſe diſputes, and the diligence of the Kings agents continually about the head quarters, it was verily expected, that at <hi>Honnſlow-heath,</hi> a very great part of the Army would have declared for the King.</p>
            <p>As for all the reſt of the Majors Narrative, to that at <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brook,</hi> comes to no more but this, the King ſaw his party in <hi>London</hi> was not able to compaſſe any deſign, they were ſo divided within themſelves, and that therefore it was in vain, to make thoſe his enemies who had him in cuſtody, and that the beſt courſe he could then take, in purſuance of his intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, was to ſeeme wholly theirs, upon ſuch cunning tearmes, as in time would be like bones caſt amongſt them.</p>
            <p>They on the other ſide, perceiving all this crafty dealing, were yet forced to hold faire with him, becauſe his party might otherwiſe take fire, upon the leaſt diſtaſte taken by him, which at that time might have much prejudiced them, though done him little good; for he was wholly ordered by the Scots counſell, who were then altogether unprovided, and reſolved not to ſtirre, till the Army ſhould fall into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtempers; which as the King and his politick party handled the matter, they knew would certainly be, upon their firſt freedom from a viſible adverſary; as indeed it came to paſſe.</p>
            <p>So that all the buſineſſe about the propoſalls, comes to this, that they were uſed by theſe Gentlemen as a meanes to keep the King from ſtirring, and their error was, in believing thoſe could have done it: for the King did but ſeeme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the propoſalls in all he did, but (in his heart) abhorred to come in upon any ſuch rearms, neither upon the Armies or Parliaments intereſt, as reſolving rather ſtill to hazard all, then to have any barres or bonds upon him, but ſuch as he can break a ſunder, or ſhake off at pleaſure.</p>
            <p>And therefore the whole ſeries and carriage of this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, proves no other but as a dream, the Lieut. General and Commiſ: Gen. were indeed over carefull to keepe him quiet, that could not have been troubleſome then, but to his own ruine, nor did any thing make more for the Kings advantage, then his long inſiſting, altering and tampering upon the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116868:6"/>Propoſalls, and <hi>Abſolon</hi>-like, holding diſcourſes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timacy with the Officers and Souldiers, to inſinuate himſelf in their favours, and ſteale away their hearts, chiefly in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to caſt himſelf wholly upon the Army.</p>
            <p>By all which fraudulent means, jealouſies were dayly bread, with emulations &amp; diviſions to purpoſe, which their preſent prevalencies &amp; ſucceſſe, in obtaining ſo ready a paſſage to &amp; through the City, made the Lieut. Gen. Commiſ. Gen. and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers too much to ſlight &amp; neglect, by which means, thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions ſo increaſed &amp; grew to ſuch a head, that although they were quit of their fears from <hi>London,</hi> yet greater and more dangerous diſtractions remained amongſt themſelves, as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe their Councells at <hi>Kingſton</hi> and <hi>Putney:</hi> which alſo bread ſo great a diſcontent between the generall Officers and Adjutators, that the Officers knew not which way to reſolve upon for their own ſecurity.</p>
            <p>All which diſtractions were not a little fomented by <hi>Bartley Aſhburnham, Beſwell</hi> &amp; others the Kings inſtruments, with the chiefe Officers had moſt correſpondency, to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther diſlike and complaint of the Adjutators, ſo that heats were dayly ſtruck between them; all which made for the Kings deſign, who as their differences increaſed, he miniſters more and more occaſions, keepes (as it were) open houſe at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, reſolves and gives out, that he will not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part thence, except to <hi>London,</hi> invites and intertains thouſands both of City and Country to viſit him, ingratiates himſelf openly with <hi>Londoners,</hi> Souldiers, and all reſorters; and thus in effect, he becomes Maſter of his Maſters; nor could thoſe who gave him this liberty to their own prejudice, now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain him, but to their greater prejudice: for at this time, his party began a freſh, and (as if by direction) to take ſuch heart, that his intereſt is not only the moſt frequent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe at head quarters, but openly maintained in all compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and what courſe then to hinder it appeated not.</p>
            <p>Which intricat buſineſſes thus occurring, made the Army not only to deal ſo gently with their unjuſt oppoſers in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, as finding the King upon their diviſions, was grown ſomewhat formidable to them, but to alter their purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſo often about purging the Houſe; for they having been
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116868:7"/>looſers by their gentlenes to the King, were loath to hazard the making ſo great a party their deſperate enemies.</p>
            <p>For now their work was made extream difficult, the ſcean or face of things was wholly changed, the grievances and cauſe of the people, which they had eſpouſed and undertaken, was quite layed aſide, to the great grief of the Adjutators, and all men who had affixed ſo great hopes on them, and they were forced to take new Councels meerly to preſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p>So that all this Majors Narrative of what one ſaid and did at one time, and what another did or ſaid at another time, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the King or from him, or concerning the Parliament, or any of the Members or Votes, comes all to nothing, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe neceſſity makes them ſo, againſt which there is no plea; but all that can be ſaid may be ſummed up in this totall, <hi>the King was too ſutle for them in the art of King-craſt,</hi> and their dear-bought experience (no doubt) will warne them from dealing any more with him at that weapon, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>another ſo juſt, ſo tryed a one,</hi> as yet in their own hands.</p>
            <p>Yet as skilfull as he was, they foyled him ſhrewdly at his own weapon in getting him ſo ſuddainly into the Iſle of <hi>Wight.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems, by ſo long practiſe with him they found, that he lay moſt open <hi>to fear,</hi> &amp; no marvel, having ſo guilty a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, ſo that although the buſslings of <hi>Martin, Rainsborrouh</hi> and the new commotions of the new Agents, put them to much care and trouble, yet they made a ſeaſonable uſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, to affright his Majeſty out of his hold at <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, and from his more advantagious reſolution of comming to <hi>London,</hi> where he was dayly and hourly by his friends ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, by which ſo timely and needfull an act, they ſecured both themſelves and the Agents party from ſuch a danger, as would have put them into new motions and further divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: And though the buſines of the Agents ended not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further trouble, yet was this conveyance of the King from <hi>Hampton</hi> Court, the firſt and principall means that made way for union in the Army; which that it proved ſo, ſeemes to be this Majors extream trouble and vexation.</p>
            <p>For whats the cauſe of all theſe his ſtories? but by his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueing the memory of all miſcarriages, differences, jealouſies,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116868:7"/>unkindneſſes, weakneſſes, affronts, quarrels, ſlaunders, arts, policies and the like, where with theſe ſhattered times did moſt unhappily abound, to eaſt them all again into new divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and diſtempers, which is ſtill his Maſters work, and without which he ſees (not withſtanding all riſings, revoltings and the Scots to boote) he is not likely to prevaile: and this moſt baſe and vile end, this unworthy Major moſt labours with all his might, not only by lies, but by ſome truths more maliciouſly uſed then lies, to compaſſe his ungodly deſigne.</p>
            <p>But for all his miſchievous haſt, he comes too lare, <hi>the burnt children are ſufficiently warned, no Tutor being ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full as experience;</hi> the Officers and Souldiers have learned at dear rates, to ſhun a Courtier as they would do a Leaper, or as a penitent man would ſhun the tempter: ſo that old things are paſt away, and all are become new.</p>
            <p>The parliament and the Army are friends, and the Army are at unity within themſelves, all minding and intending the publik good and common freedom of the Nation, all jarres and ſcarres are healed, all are hearty true and reall Friends, no by-names nor ſcandalous diſtinctions are mentioned amongſt them; ſo united are they in affection, though far diſtant in their preſent imployment, that whereas this Major thinks by this his treachery to divide them, or at leaſt to expoſe theſe Gentlemen, the Lieut. Generall, and Com. Generall to the condemnation of the Army, and thereby to render them uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in theſe dangerous times, when their experienced abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties are ſo much needed, and poſſibly alſo to expoſe their lives to danger, as a ſacrifice more pleaſing to his Maſter, then that of Sr. <hi>Iohn Hotham</hi> his firſt, as theſe his greateſt oppoſers. — all works the contrary, their preſent actions, fidelity, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimity and ingenuous frequent acknowledgment of unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed truſts to men of corrupt principles, and their admitting into their hearts too great eſtimation of the King and his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties power, contrary to that wonderfull experience of Gods mighty power and providence, which ſo mightily went forth and alongs with them and their Armies, together with their great reſpect manifeſted to men of integrity, though former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at ſome diſtance, and their diſlike of flatterers and time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers; This, this ſincerity in them, hath ſo renewed the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116868:8"/>of the whole Army to them, that a haire of their heads (whil'ſt they ſo continue,) is not be touch't, &amp; the evill this unworthy Major intends againſt them, turns to their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, yea and for any good he hath herein done for the King his Maſter, he had as good played the laſt Act of <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophell,</hi> then thus to have either acted, or Councelled or ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken againſt thoſe gentlemen, whereby he is become hatefull to himſelf and friends, and uſeles to all parties.</p>
            <p>Thus much may ſuffice, in reference to their actions and deſigns, ſomewhat is yet neceſſary to be ſpoken, concerning their principles.</p>
            <p>As firſt, he charges them to hold <hi>that every fingle man is judge of juſt and right, as to the good or ill of a Kingdom.</hi> Put caſe now Major, the Parliament (of whoſe honour you would be thought to be ſo tender) ſhould Command you to take up <hi>Armes</hi> and kill and ſlay ſuch a man, or ſort of men, admit your judgment and conſcience tells you, thoſe men have done no wrong, or that thoſe things are juſt and good, for which the Parliament commands you to kill and ſlay them: who is judge in this caſe? Are not you a murtherer if you obey them? Who is Judge if you obey them nor? Certainly, this principle would not have offended you, had not your conſcience been ſtifled with ambition and mercinary gaine.</p>
            <p>Their ſecond principle he ſaith is, <hi>that the intereſt of honeſt men is the intereſt of the Kingdom,</hi> and the truth is, the intereſt of honeſt men is an honeſt intereſt, and if the Kingdoms in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt hath not been ſo, or is not ſo, yet that it ought to be ſo, who will gainſay? nor is an honeſt intereſt ſo hard to be diſcerned in theſe diſcourſive and experimentall times: But the Lieutenant Gen might be confident, that thoſe only were honeſt, who were conformable to his judgment; for who thinks him not able to judge of publike right? Believe it, thoſe that throughly know him, do teſtifie his ability ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently: And as for his engageing of Col. <hi>Rains borough;</hi> its wel known that <hi>Rainsborough</hi> is mettle paſt bowing or warping, and its an Argument, the Lieut. Generalls intereſt was cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly juſt, when Col. <hi>Rainsborough</hi> would promiſe confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity to him and the Com: Generall.</p>
            <p>Their third principle he ſayes is, <hi>that it is lawfull to paſſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116868:8"/>through any formes of Government, for the accompliſhing of his ends;</hi> now its known, his ends alwayes propoſed have been publike freedom and ſafety, and who in theſe knowing times is ſo ignorant, as to deny ſo undoubted a truth? Are not all formes of Government appointed to thoſe ends? Now, if any Government ſhall become ſo farre degenerate, as to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or betray the juſt liberty and due ſafety of the people, doth it not utterly expire in it ſelf, and ceaſe to be any more a Government, but rather a meere confuſion.</p>
            <p>Is not <hi>Salus populi, ſuprema lex?</hi> Or is any form, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Argument, Law, objection, or exception to be pleaded againſt the freedom &amp; ſafety of the people? No certainly: ſo that this principle being rightly applyed &amp; wel under ſtood, is ſo far from diſparaging theſe Gentlemen, that nothing could be an occaſion of their greater honour, then that it may be recorded and related to all poſterities, the whole courſe of their actions manifeſted, <hi>this was their undoubted principle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their 4 and laſt principle, he ſayes is, <hi>that its lawful to play the knave with a knave,</hi> ſuch a phraſe of ſpeech any of them might occaſionally expreſs, as being a common ſaying, but that they meant as he would have them underſtood, appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, it being generally taken in a more tolerable ſenſe, as to deceive the deceiver, which is excuſed by <hi>Huſhies</hi> policie, in deſtroying the corrupt Councell of <hi>Achitophell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But wiſe and good men may ſomtimes be more apt (in way of diſcourſe) to ſpeak of ſuch a thing, then at any time to practice it; and no doubt, but foreſight &amp; reſolution prevents the need of it, the ſucceſs thereof ſeldom anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the expectation, one evill, (yea the leaſt) ſeldom eſcaping without producing another; and ſo alſo it cometh to paſſe, with thoſe that make uſe of a K. to catch a K. as may be ſeen by their uſing of <hi>this Major</hi> in all they imployed him; which may be a ſufficient warning for them henceforth, to take heed what ſort of men they truſt, there being hardly any vain glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious flattering or covetous men employed by them, but one way or other they are prejudiced and diſparaged by them.</p>
            <p>And though this treacherous Major (for a concluſion to his accuſation) would induce all men to believe, that if theſe Gentlemen thus principled ſhall prevaile by the Army, they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116868:9"/>intend to deſtroy the power and authority of Parliament; (for which he ſaies he engaged, beleive him thoſe that can) yet if their demeanour towards the Parliament in generall upon their late ſucceſſe, and their gentle bearing towards their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt oppoſers, from whom not one drop of blood, nor one pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of mony hath been drawn nor taken, they all being out of trouble, impriſonment, exile and fear, and ſo in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability may ſtill continue, except they make to themſelves new occaſions, by contrivances and Perſonall Treaties.</p>
            <p>If theſe and the like carriages and inclinations in them, be duly weighed, it wilbe impoſſible for any conſtruction to be made, but that moſt earneſtly they deſire to ſee the Common-wealth reſtored to a certaine condition of juſt and true free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſafety and peace by this Parliament, according to the truſt repoſed in them, and would rejoyce that it might nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be deferred, nor done to halves nor parcels, which (as all men ſee) doth cauſe new and perpetuall troubles.</p>
            <p>And theſe their juſt deſires and reſolutions being perceived by this Malignant Major, hath cauſed him at this time to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in his colours, to acquite his command, and to fall upon this courſe, to put the Parliament, Army and Kingdom into further diſtempers, and there by to render them more inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of making oppoſition either againſt the Scots or other forraign forces or inteſtine enemies, which have riſen up in ſo many places for the King his Maſter, againſt the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Army.</p>
            <p>But it availeth nothing, God is mercifull, hath fetcht them home by repentance, made them to ſee &amp; be ſencible of their errours, paſſes ever their many failings and infirmities, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains with them ſtill, bleſſing them with ſucceſs upon ſucceſs even to admiration: and doubtles will continue ſo to do, if yet they ſhall vigorouſly ſet themſelves to do his work, in ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing all kinds of tiranny &amp; oppreſſion in whomſoever, &amp; in clearing and ſecuring the liberty, peace &amp; ſafety of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, according to their many promiſes &amp; engagments, and for which juſt ends, God hath raiſed, proſpered &amp; preſerved them, —but let them henceforth beware of ſhewing reſpect to perſons in judgment, and of that curſe which certainly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth all thoſe that do the work of the Lord negligently.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
